[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software this is Sam tagert for SE radio
I'm here today with Emily be to talk
about katas and the importance of
practice Emily is an independent
consultant YouTuber and Technical coach
she's the author of two books related to
coaching and teaches courses for plural
slite in O'Reilly she founded the seman
technical coaching Society in order to
promote technical excellence and support
coaches welcome Emily thank you it's
lovely to be with you here today so to
get started you're most wellknown or at
least I know you best for your
collection of katas so maybe we could
start by talking about what is a Kata
well it's a small coding exercise that
you can use to practice skills and get
better at things like refactoring and
test driven development so often Ks are
associated with code Retreats or
coaching are these exercises that I can
just go do on my own well yes I mean a
lot of software developers will do that
they'll just find an hour or so that
they've got time to practice and open
the code Carter in your favorite IDE or
editor and you get to choose from a
number of different programming
languages for most of them or some of
them are just from scratch and you can
you start with an empty editor some of
them you start with a piece of code that
you need to refactor and build on and
then you you can just spend the time
writing the best possible code in the
best possible way and improving your
coding skills great so do you ever have
trouble selling this practice idea to
management I assume people are doing
this like during their work time
sometimes do you ever get any push back
for manag because I can imagine some
managers saying well you know you want
to learn but why don't you just learn on
the job like why is practicing outside
of normal daily work useful
well the thing with a code cutter is
it's a lot simpler than your production
code so you can really focus on the
skills and the moves of coding well and
gain the fluency that you need to be
able to do that in your production code
later on so if you spend some time
practicing doing a particular
refactoring using your shortcuts you'll
find that when you need those same
things in your production code later
they'll come to you more easily you'll
be able to code more quickly and get the
code into the editor and your production
code more fluently and easily and better
and raise the quality of your work so I
think I mean whether you should do that
on work time I mean some people have
argued that you should do this on your
free time as a kind of investment in
your own skills and your personal
development I think that's a little
shortsighted for employers to think that
developers are going to do that I think
it's actually in everyone's interest
that there is at least a small amount of
work time allocated for personal
developments and getting better at your
job everyone wins from developers
improving the whole time so those are
the kind of things that I would say to
managers it doesn't need to be a lot of
time but some time spent practicing and
improving will benefit the organization
as a whole and could time that leads
into my next question which is how often
do you recommend that developers do
katas is this like a daily weekly
monthly type of thing well I mean it
depends a lot on your previous skills
and knowledge and how much pressure
there is in your project because you
don't want to be doing this kind of
practice if you're feeling really
pressured and there's a lot going on and
you don't have the head space or on the
other hand it could be a good way to
relax and calm down if you're in a
really stressful situation but still I
think it's got to be agreed with the
team and the individual and their
manager but something like you know an
hour of Sprint should be all right or a
couple of hours a Sprint maybe yeah yeah
so can you talk a little bit your
comment earlier remind me about where
katas come from cuz I used to do like
some martial arts and I feel like in
martial arts you do the katas and it's
about like building muscle memory is
that like similar when you're talking
about like shortcuts and things like
that yeah so this idea of fluency things
that you can do without really having to
think a lot about it it's an aspect of
skill so being a knowing how to do a
refactoring like so one of the code
Cutters I want to e an example here one
of the code Cutters I like is parrot it
allows you to practice the moves of
converting a switch statement a
conditional into polymorphism with class
hierarchy and usually there are a few
steps to this conversion and it's not
something you need to do every day when
you're working your production code but
when you do it's good to know the moves
and know how to do it safely and extend
your design and make it more extensible
for the future so a bit of time spent
practicing on the parrot code Carter
means that you've just got all those
moves kind of yeah like you say in your
muscle memory and it goes much more
smoothly when you need to do that in
your production code there's a
difference between knowing on in theory
what the moves are and having practiced
them and being able to just bring them
out you've got so much more brain
capacity left over for the rest of your
job basically yeah the other thing I've
noticed about kadas In the comparison to
martial arts is like doing martial arts
you do a kada and if you have somebody
watching you like an instructor they'll
come in and they'll just like tweak one
little thing and then you practice again
and you it makes it very easy to focus
by doing it over and over again you can
focus on like tiny little details have
you noticed that yeah although I mean
it's not usually somebody else observing
me I'm observing myself and often it's
like I think there should be a better
way to do this and looking like my tools
have extensive refracturing capabilities
a lot of which I don't know as well as I
could so it's about thinking H is there
an easier way to do this there's a lot
of manual steps in this part of the
refactor ing let's see if there's a good
way to do this with the tool instead so
reflecting on your own habits and how
you're working is part of doing a cter
yeah and some people publish like so I
publish now demos of me doing code cters
like little videos and that can be a way
to go back and oh you could do it like
that too maybe I should try that in my
tools yeah I find it interesting every
time I do them you can kind of just you
end up at a slightly different place
every time right right so that's a
different with the martial arts CU I I
get the feeling with the martial arts
you're supposed to do it the same every
time and there's some kind of Ideal that
you're heading towards whereas that's
not the case with a code Carter you
probably do it differently every time
and learn something different every time
and that's part of the joy of it
actually that that you're continually
learning and improving yeah it's not
about doing it the same every time I
think in the martial arts it can be used
that way I think often it's used cuz
people are trying to get promoted to
like new belt or something and so like
they have to do it exactly the way they
instructor wants them to do it and it's
kind of graded whereas like when you're
doing code kadas for yourself and coding
for me it's always like it's just
exploration it's kind of almost like a
fun playful thing of like let's start
here and see where we end up and see you
know what happens if I use this one tool
as opposed to another if I triy this you
I did these two refactorings but maybe
what if I do them in the opposite order
does that lead me somewhere else or
something like that yeah absolutely yeah
being playful and creative and learning
more about how to to code well and there
aren't any wrong answers you know
there's no way to do a code Carter wrong
well actually if you break all the tests
and the code doesn't work at the end
then yeah okay but you know within the
reasonable definition of success there
are a lot of ways to solve a code cutter
yeah you hit on something too the other
thing I like to practice when I practice
them is taking those small steps because
I I feel like one of the problems in
software engineering is we try to take
too big a step sometimes so breaking
things down into smaller steps I find
quite useful
well it's the classic isn't it how do
you solve a big problem while you break
it into pieces and the skill of being
able to take you know you've got a goal
for where you want the design to go and
being able to break down the steps to
how to get to that design and how to
build the pieces and make it work at
each stage there's a huge benefit in
being able to work that way so that the
code is working after each of those
small steps rather than trying to take
one giant leap and the code being broken
for a long time in between the kind of
the style of coding where you can work
in small steps I think is is more
effective you're more in control and you
also have more opportunities to change
direction and end up in a better place
than the one you first envisaged yeah I
always think about that is taking big
steps could get you there faster but
it's always more risky like by taking
those smaller steps you're guaranteeing
that like as you go along you're not
breaking things because if you make that
big step and you do it all at once and
it works hey that's great you just saved
a ton of time but if it doesn't work
then you spend a bunch of time going
back back and trying to figure out
what's wrong and it tends to take a lot
of extra time a lot of software
developers aren't really aware of that
and I think just practicing on code
Carters gives you that awareness of
actually I've spent too long on this I
should have had passing tests by now
maybe I need to rethink and back up and
and try again and you can do that in a
code cutter in a way that you might not
in production code yeah so you mentioned
there are different types of skills that
you can practice with code what are some
of the skills that you can practice and
give us some examples of how you would
practice ice those I'm quite a fan of
refactoring Carters so like parrot that
I mentioned before for practicing a
particular transformation of a design a
lot of the refactoring Carters though
actually you start with code that has a
really bad design and very little
structure and the challenge of those
ones is to practice cleaning it up and
imposing a structure and getting to a
point where the design is easier to
understand and extend often a
refactoring Carter has a new requirement
that you need to implement and before
that's going to be feasible you've got
to get the code into a better State
using lots of smaller refactorings so
that's one aspect just getting better
and more fluent with transforming a
design from one place to another another
thing that people practice of course is
just test driven development starting
with just a problem description some
code that you need to write and an empty
editor how do we get there using tdd
which is like the first test that you
write what happens when that fails and
what design you come up with and what
steps you take after that so how do you
break down that problem into steps and
Implement them test by test so that's a
great use of code Carters and honestly
those are the two main things tdd and
refactoring okay so if I understand
correctly like the tdd tests basically
those work in any language very easily
because you don't need any pre-existing
code right you just sit down with a
problem statement and you just start is
that basically how it works yeah okay
and is is there Variety in those or they
all basically just like here's an
exercise good start like are there ways
to practice different aspects of tdd or
different types of tdd well I mean I've
been playing with this a bit because tdd
as a discipline it's quite big there are
lots of aspects to tdd and to be
successful with it you need a lot of
skills you need you know like the skill
to design a test case you need the skill
to be able to refactor away away
duplication that you may have introduced
like by triangulation you need the skill
of just taking that problem and breaking
it into steps and what order to do them
in there's a bunch of other things
involved and that it's if you're not
very experienced with tdd doing all of
that at once in the first place is quite
difficult so I've been trying to
experiment with well what if we give
people the list of test cases and say so
here's a description of the problem and
here's a description of the test cases
in the order that you should do them in
or what if we actually give them the
test cases just kind of like commented
out and get them to implement them one
by one cuz then you've removed some of
the challenge of tdd you've removed the
part we have to break down the problem
or you've removed the part we have to
design the test cases so that people can
focus on other aspects like just working
in small steps and refactoring after
each one so I I've got a few Cutters
which I've tried to do that with and I'm
actively using these in the kind of
training and coaching that I do so there
are some which are bit like that yeah
we'll talk more about the training and
coaching in a little bit so some other
questions I have so for the refactoring
cadas what languages do these exist in
are they available in any language most
of them are most of them specific to a
language or a language feature right
we're practicing refactoring there's
certain refactorings that only work in
certain languages like certain patterns
things like that well yeah I mean my
most famous refracturing Carter is the
Gilded Rose and that's translated in
like 50 odd languages some of them very
surprising it turns out you can write
bad procedural style code in pretty much
any programming language
and I'm constantly surprised I've got a
translation like uml which I an xslt I
mean these are not mainstream kind of
things you think of as programming
languages so code Carters can be
available in a lot of strange languages
but really it's all um volunteer efforts
so when I create a refactoring Carter I
obviously do it in one language that
occurs to me and then usually I'll
translate it into the two or three
languages that I might use when I'm
training and coaching people and then
it's all up there on Open Source on on
GitHub and people send me pull requests
with translations so a lot of the
Carters are available in a lot of
languages and it's it's not primarily me
who's done all those translations most
of the time you also hit on something
else that I found and that is you talk
about writing bad code I find it very
hard to write bad code sometimes when
I'm trying to come up with an example of
like oh don't do this like it's almost
and maybe it's because I've practiced a
lot but that like muscle memory it's
like I have to force to do it the wrong
way do do you run into that at all yeah
so a lot of the refracturing Carters are
inspired by production code that I've
seen I've thought oh this was really
difficult to refactor I think I need to
make an exercise out of this so that's
inspiration for quite a lot of them but
some of them it is I've thought it
through and thought I need an exercise
for practicing this particular
refracturing can I construct an example
that needs that so some of them are more
constructed and yeah it's I don't always
succeed in making something that's
realistic but you know some of them are
better than others so yeah you you
mentioned production Cod so how well do
skills transfer from okay I learned how
to do this in the Kata Can you talk
about some examples of where you've seen
teams that were struggling with
something and then somehow by doing
these katas they learned some skills
that they were able to apply oh yeah
yeah so I mean this happens when I'm
coaching because it's there was one team
I was working with recently and we would
do the coaching like I would do a
learning hour where we would practice on
a code Carter and then to work in their
production code afterwards all together
and we were using exactly the same
skills in the session afterwards and
sometimes it just works really well and
you think yeah actually this learning
hour we're going to use it straight away
in the next coaching session so that's
kind of one of my goals I think when I'm
coaching to try and come up with a
learning hour that's totally relevant to
their situation I can say this
particular team they had some C code
that was pretty old and a Long Function
that was really long and complex and
that they didn't fully understand um the
naming was really poor it was doing far
too much and it needed migrating to C++
to a more object-oriented design to a
more modern way of doing things and we
first spent a lot of time getting it
under test and we used a lot of approval
testing and and combination approvals
and we got it all under test so that we
could then refactor with confidence and
then we did a lot of refactoring
exercises and learned about extracting
methods moving methods reducing the
scope of variables yeah all sorts of
refactorings that I've got exercises for
practicing yeah that brings up an
interesting point are there any c is
where like you take for example a lot of
places are move trying to move away from
object R code into more functional code
or there exercises to like take object
or code and transform it into functional
code or vice versa or translate between
the two is that a thing oh that's a good
idea I don't just at the moment I can't
think that I've got any exercises that
are quite like that if the code is
well-designed object-oriented code I
don't think it's a huge problem to then
translate that to a more functional
design she says confidently I don't know
I'm not an expert with functional
programming myself I've done a little
bit but it's not really my focus the
problem that I see much more often is
that the code just doesn't have very
good design it's pretty procedural like
long Tangled
awkward badly named just and so just
getting any kind of structure into that
is a bonus that's much more likely to be
my focus than code that's already all
right and just needs to be more
functional okay you wrote a book about
coding dojos can you talk a little bit
about like what a coding Dojo is so code
Carters have been around for a long time
it was Dave Thomas in his blog who
proposed the idea after watching his
son's karate practice
so that was in like I don't know 2002
2003 something like that when I first
read about code Carters and started
practicing on them and I was getting
somewhere and enjoying this but I felt
that it was difficult to get the people
in my team to pay any attention to the
idea of testure and development or or
doing code Cutters I did try but it
didn't really seem to stick and then I
just I went to this conference in 2005
where these two French guys Lauren
bossavit and Emanuel gu
we're showing their coding Dojo that
they just set up in Paris and they came
to this conference to show us what it
was like to come to their coding dojo
and I thought well this is great this is
a way of having a group meeting where
you get everyone who wants together to
do some code Cutters together and we
learn from one another and we support
one another and we start having a
discussion about tdd and how to do that
and this seemed to me to be exactly what
I needed to get my colleagues on board
with with doing tdd so I went back to my
organization and I brought in lauron
actually he came and gave us some
training so that we could get started
with this and it kind of just went from
there really that I started leading
coding dojo and I was doing it with
local user groups as a way to start that
conversation and get people interested
and show what tdd actually is and it
seemed to me to be a good way for a
group of peers to kind of learn from one
another so that was what led to me to
write that book because I found it
worked so well for that so that leads me
to another question about just katas in
general if I'm a developer and I find
one of these CS I want to go practice it
do you recommend doing it by yourself do
you recommend doing it in in a Ensemble
as a pair what or all of the above well
yeah basically I mean if you're the only
person in your team who's even vaguely
interested you might want to just try it
out by yourself to start with so you get
some practice and you understand the
idea of what you're supposed to do with
a Carter so you can absolutely use it by
yourself if you can get a group together
of people who are willing to try it it
can be much more fun you know you get
that kind of group camaraderie going and
you can support one another and and talk
about when you run into difficulties and
you can do all together as a group
Ensemble style or you can split into
pairs it's a little bit less
intimidating actually to do it in pairs
and then you join together and discuss
what you will found at the end so both
those ways do you have any examples of
like some of the learnings that take
place from like watching other people
write code like from that PA Ensemble
thing oh right well when you're in an
ensemble and and somebody's at the
keyboard that you haven't seen code
before they're bound to be using aspects
of their IDE and environment that you
haven't seen before and You' be like oh
how did you do that and it's a great way
to just pick up General coding tips it's
particularly useful for people in the
same organization who actually have
access to all the same tools and maybe
just don't know what you can do with
them to spread knowledge in a team
that's something I find often that
programmers come out of a onom like oh I
didn't know you could do that that's so
cool I'm gonna do that now the
interesting thing I found is sometimes
even the more experienced people learn a
lot because like you learn a certain set
of shortcuts in an IDE and then they
come out with a new version and it has
some new add-ons that and maybe you
missed the press release or whatever you
didn't see it and then you see somebody
else do something you're like wait you
can do that I didn't know you could do
that yeah yeah or it happens vice versa
that you're doing do something the long
way one of the younger more Junior
developers is like why are you doing it
that way there's a much easier way and
you're like really and so yeah I find
that quite interesting absolutely
matches my experience great so I'm
curious what are the challenges with
creating your own kadas like if I'm a
developer like say I work in a team is
it better to cry and create kadas that
mimic some of the problems that I see on
my team or is it better to go use the
existing ones do you have any advice on
that
I think creating a code Carter is a
little bit more difficult than it looks
so it's a good idea to try out some of
the existing ones first if you don't
know which Carter to choose there are
lots of experienced coaches out there
who will probably be able to advise I
mean I've got a community of of coaches
and quite often people will say oh
what's the best Carter to use for you
know domain driven design practicing
this aspect or whatever people just pose
questions my needs to learn this skill
what's a good Carter for that and people
will be able to give you suggestions so
that's one thing to do first but if
you've got a bit of an experience and
you think there's a gap and there needs
to be a new Carter for particular
refactoring or whatever it is absolutely
give it a go and share your work again
there are technical coaches out there
who are generous with their time and
will give you some advice and say oh
this is good have you thought about
doing it like this or who might
translate your C into other languages
and I don't know there's a bunch of
people out there who are willing to help
yeah the biggest challenge I've kind of
found in trying to create not
necessarily C but just like examples for
things is it's hard to find something
that's relevant and yet simple enough to
explain the problem without it being
like overly simple and people are like
well okay yeah that solution's obvious
so like why would I do you know have you
run into that at all usually the
opposite problem I mean when I've been
designing Carters my tendency is to make
them too difficult and too complex and
have too many steps to complete them I
think there's a huge value in very small
examples that you can complete in half
an hour you know that's a good size of
of problem where you can just come from
code that doesn't kind of look good to
code that does look good in a short time
and it can explain a principle like what
is a fake or how do you use delegation
instead of inheritance you know that
brings up another question about koca so
like how long like does a typical code C
take like an hour or do you like time
box them usually and say I'm just going
to work on this for an hour and see
where I get or how does that work yeah
you you time box them I mean if you get
over enthusiastic you can just spend
hours and hours doing them so you
shouldn't do that it's more effective if
you practice short and often I reckon
and I think a good code Carter you can
get somewhere with it in half an hour
and in an hour hopefully when you
perhaps not the first time you do it but
when you've done it a few times you can
complete it in an hour that's probably
about right and less or less I mean
definitely less some of the exercises I
do I've got demos of them and I complete
them in 10 to 15 minutes sometimes less
well one of the things I run into with
the refactoring code is sometimes like
when to stop right like you've done the
main point of the exercise but you're
like oh I could polish this I could
change this I could change that at some
point you're just like okay that that's
good enough do you run into that at all
well yeah I mean there's diminishing
returns some point you're just kind of
tweaking and the design is equally good
for adding whatever feature it was you
were trying to add although I think you
can still learn from that if
particularly if you're getting more
fluent with your shortcuts and the
Transformations you're making are still
improving the code then I mean you can
spend time just tweaking designs and I
don't think that's wasted time
necessarily okay yeah well it's learning
so I guess learning is always valuable I
guess you just going to have to balance
that against the demands of uh whatever
you're working on yeah and also where
your sources of feedback are it can be
quite useful if you've worked on it by
yourself to show the design you come up
with to someone else and see well do you
think it'd be worth doing it like this
instead or continuing to tweak and they
might have some good feedback for you I
think that tweaking though is also
somewhat useful in the sense that you
learn how long it takes to do certain
things and sometimes then you be like
okay well I could tweak this but it's
easy to do later so I'll just put that
off until I actually need it CU I feel
like sometimes people try to like pre-
optimize things and like oh I might need
this in the future so I'm I'll just
refactor it this way and it's like I've
kind of learn to just it works the test
pass I'm fairly happy with it I just
kind of let it sit until I have a need
to go back and start tweaking it in
order to add some new feature something
when you get fluent with refracturing
you can actually make quite big changes
quite easily so yeah I think it's good
to have that experience of realizing oh
actually when I'm good at my shortcuts
and I know what I'm doing I can do that
change when I need it I don't need to do
now yeah I don't know that I've ever
actually like made that connection
between that and practice but I think
that is part of what it is is having
practiced it a bunch and getting fluent
with it and also I think part of it too
is the Tooling in the IDE too like if
you actually have good Tooling in your
IDE and you actually know so one of the
things that I use Kus for actually is
building IDE tooling so like I'll build
some IDE tools to do some refactoring
then I'll try them out on AATA and see
how it flows and I I find that quite
useful to give me feedback on like okay
yeah this workflow makes sense or
doesn't oh that sounds really cool yeah
so kadas and this practice is part of
what you do but you also have this thing
called Salon coaching that kind of
encompasses some of the stuff from Kus
can can you talk about what does the
term Salon mean what is Salon coaching
how does it relate to
kadas well saman is a Swedish word it
means together I chose this as the name
for my style of technical coaching just
to make it possible to like Google and
find other people who know about it so
it's a style of technical coaching that
combines two main elements one of which
is like code Carters in the form of a a
learning hour and the other part is
Ensemble so a technical coach works with
developers and development teams to help
them to improve the way they work raise
the quality of their code increase their
productivity and and happiness when
they're working and the samon method
then is the particular style that I use
with with these two main elements so it
relates to code cart is in that in order
to do learning hours you need a good
supply of of exercises to bring in the
learning hour ads to the code Carter
though just as well as being a chance to
to do a bit of coding practice the the
learning hour structures it as a
one-hour session that you do with a team
and making sure that it's as interactive
as possible and there are opportunities
for discussion so that you're building
not only the skills of the participants
but starting to build up a a culture and
a way of talking about coding and
learning the words that you use when
you're talking about design and and
coding techniques so learning hour is
got more structure than just a coding
Dojo or a code Carter by itself so you
mentioned communication do you have any
examples of that like communication like
spreading like to other aspects of the
organization like outside of like the
learning hours have you noticed that
improving in other areas the kind of
communication I'm talking about is
really between Developers within the
team so it's like learning the words for
things like we're trying to move the
design towards ports and adapters or
we're trying to increase the code
coverage but we know what that means
we're trying to increase the support
that the unit test give us for
refactoring rather than some number on a
graph somewhere so it's it's really
about communication between developers
the way I notice these sessions helping
is that then in Ensemble session which
is the other part of the coaching where
we go into their production code
suddenly the team members are allowed
able to explain to one another what
they're trying to do more effectively
and they'll they'll talk about the code
design that they're trying to aim for
more fluently and in a way that the
whole team is on board with that's kind
of where I notice it that reminds me of
like books like the design patterns
books and some of the refractor books
like the code smells of just like
putting names to things does your
coaching like go over a lot of that type
of stuff as
well yeah absolutely I mean the design
pattern book is really old now but it's
still you know relevant to know what a
factory is and a single turn and these
words should be familiar to all but
they're not always it's the same with
the refactorings and cod smells they're
pretty old ideas but knowing the names
of them helps you to communicate more
effectively so you can sit with your
team and say I think we've got feature
Envy here and then they might hopefully
know what you mean by that and the
they'll be able to work more effectively
afterwards because they'll see that
they'll be able to talk about it and say
oh yeah and this is what we do when we
have feature Envy you know yeah is there
a way that you have to measure like the
effectivess of coaching like do you have
a way method to like say okay we went in
and coached and then can you do you like
observe them later in their own quote
natural habitat or something to see like
okay yeah these ideas stuck or do you
have any sense of that so one aspect of
the samon method is that you're not
full-time with the team you have a a
more intense period where you are you're
sitting with them quite often over a
period of a few weeks maybe and then you
you go away and perhaps you work with a
different team or do something else and
then you come back and one measure of
your success as a coach is when you come
back are they still doing the things
that you were hoping that they would be
doing that you were doing last time you
saw them when you were all together so
that's a big motivator for me it's
trying to work out well what can we
achieve in this coaching block that
they're still going to be able to be
doing when I come back for the next one
do you have like a success story of a
particular team that that really
embodies that so one of the things I do
is pair coaching and I've pair coached
with lell and Falco who's another very
experienced technical coach and this was
where I really saw the effectiveness of
these these techniques was when I was
working with one of his teams and I sat
in this Ensemble and I was just
observing I wasn't part of it and one of
the people would step up and take the
Navigator role and start talking to
their teammates and saying oh we need to
do a test for this and it should be like
this and we need to set up the data like
this in the arrange step and then the
next person would step up the timer
would ring and and the Navigator role
would rotate and the next person would
step up and be able to just carry on and
they were doing test driven developments
and they were producing code with tests
that had a good design I was like Wow
they've got this they've really got this
and this was like the fifth or sixth
time lellan had been had a coaching
block with this team and he was like
yeah yeah they've got this they hardly
need me anymore and that that was really
really encouraging that technical
coaching does work and I haven't I have
to say with the teams that I've coached
I haven't been back often enough yet I
think to see that kind of effect yet I
tend to have been more spreading myself
a bit thinner and seeing a lot more
teams and having perhaps a smaller
effect but I think the if long-term
technical coaching really can transform
the practice of a team very good so you
mentioned that someon coaching has two
parts do you always do them in the same
order like one session has two parts
with the Ensemble and the learning hour
do you do them in the same order and how
does one drive the other and can you
give some examples of that the order is
not fixed my preference at the moment is
to do the learning hour first and then
The Ensemble just because I'm hoping
that we're going to learn some new skill
in the learning hour or some new words
or new vocabulary that we can then apply
directly in the production code when we
come to The Ensemble part and that
should be the case at least some of the
time although not every learning hour is
practicing a skill that's directly
relevant for today quite sometimes we
just learning speculatively about skills
and and things that we're going to need
in the future perhaps not even this
coaching block perhaps next coaching
block or the one after that so it's not
really important that you do the
learning hour first but still the goal
is always that the team should be
learning new things and opening New
Horizons and new ways of communicating
yeah I feel like it could be like a
chicken in the egg problem right because
you do the learning hour and you just
you learn a new skill and then you go
apply it but also like sometimes you
you're working in the code base and
you're like oh that skill would be
useful and then you go back and and do
the next one you do a learning hour
right something like that yeah so if if
I've got the breathing space between
these sessions you know so each session
is like half a day with the learning
hour and The Ensemble if I've got a half
a day or a few days between and before
the next one then sometimes I will be
able to prepare a completely new
learning hour to address that particular
skill that I've noticed that they need
and that's really rewarding when I can
get that to work it doesn't always
happen that way sometimes it's the next
coaching block by the time I've managed
to prepare that session that they need
do you find that a lot of teams are
already doing Ensemble programming or do
you find that when you start you spend a
lot of time teaching them just how to do
The Ensemble as opposed to like teaching
them how to do whatever skill they
learned in the learning hour oh yeah
absolutely when I'm going into most
organizations Ensemble is new and they
haven't done it before and the
developers don't have those skills so
yeah the first learning hour or perhaps
two will be focused on well what are the
roles what are you supposed to say how
do you do the
rotations yeah absolutely teaching
Ensemble skills is usually the first
thing but you know they pick that up
over the course of the the sessions by
the end of a coaching block most teams
have understood what Ensemble is they
can basically do it and they have a good
idea of when it would be useful to
continue doing that with their teams
what is the biggest challenge you face
teaching Ensemble programming there are
lots of challenges with teaching
Ensemble the first challenge is getting
people to to try it at all and be
willing that gets easier when I'm
framing it as this is part of the
coaching and you're going to learn from
one another with me mentoring you as as
a team that makes it easier to introduce
when I'm there but then once they
they've got over that hurdle and agreed
to do Ensemble the next hurdle is
helping people to feel confident to step
up and take the role of of talking or
while navigating and not be too nervous
to say anything and then to feel
confident as well to take the typist
role without feeling nervous and worried
that you're going to type the wrong
thing so it's it's mostly about creating
that safe environment where people know
what they're supposed to do and it's
okay to ask questions it's okay to go
wrong and even for senior people it's
hardest for the senior people in the
team actually because they're so used to
knowing everything comparatively to
suddenly being some kind of beginner
skill that's that can be hard for people
so it's really important for me as a
coach to put them at their ease and
reassure them and make it okay to step
into that role speaking of like being
willing to speak up and stuff do you run
into cultural issues I know you probably
deal with teams from different areas of
the world is that play a role well yeah
I have worked with teams with people
from different countries the US Europe
India and I wouldn't have said that I
mean there are cultural differences but
ensemble we were a bunch of developers
we understand code I haven't found there
to be big cultural barriers there once
you've got people to agree to try it I
haven't found it to be really too hard
okay so do most teams after they do the
salon coaching method do they continue
then to do Ensemble programming on their
own or do they mostly do that like when
they're in that learning mode yeah so
far it's mostly when I'm there a very
few teams have continued with it when
I'm not there which which I think is a
shame I would like it to be different I
think there is a huge benefit to
Ensemble even without a coach present I
think some of the teams have understood
that there have been a couple who have
continued with it and I think when I've
come back to those teams for the next
coaching Block it's been like wow okay
they have carried on with what we were
learning last time and they have
improved since I was last here so I
think there are huge benefits to it but
somehow corporate
culture it's just there seem to be a
bunch of unspoken Norms that say no we
work individually you can't you can't
work allog together that the managers
wouldn't let us even without asking the
managers you know it's just kind of
assumed that no we can't work that way
in real life I'm working on that yeah my
my immedate question was going to be is
that a a real thing or is that something
imagined by I'm sure it's probably in
some cases a bit of both right yeah I
mean of course at first glance it seems
really ineffective getting a whole team
to sit together and work on a task when
that's not normal they could get twice
you know five times as much done if five
people sat all separately I think that's
a just a misunderstanding of how
software development works I mean if
you've got a very heavy box that needs
to be carried and you ask one person to
carry it they might not be capable of
lifting that box but if you've got a
team of five they can easily lift that
box and move it much faster and it's
getting the people to understand that
software development can be like that
sometimes it takes five months Minds on
a problem to really get hold of it and
move the solution somewhere one person
on their own just just doesn't have the
mental capacity sometimes to solve some
of the programming problems that we are
facing yeah I don't know I've been
working on this analogy lately of like a
basketball team and like if the coach at
the beginning of the game said oh these
are all the tasks that we need to do and
he assigned them each to an individual
player and threw them all in their own
court with their own ball like that
might work but that's not really a team
right and like I feel like we use the
word team and then we all go work
individually that just strikes me as an
odd use of the word team sometimes right
it can be deeply ingrained in a company
culture and reward system that each
person is going to work individually and
it can be difficult to get people to see
that that's not the only way to do
things yeah the incentive structure does
not help that very much because one of
the things I've heard people say is like
okay well if we do this as a team then
who gets the credit right or who gets
the reward and it's like well you know
yeah I'm being measured how many tickets
I close each Sprint I don't get rewarded
for helping someone else close their
tickets yeah yeah so the thing is I'm a
technical coach and that's an
organizational problem that's a kind of
processed problem and there are other
coaches who are much better at those
kind of things than me people who would
work as a scrum Master an agile coach
and I'm very happy to delegate all that
side of things to them if I can I'd like
to work together with someone like that
and so that I can really just focus on
on the coding and the people writing the
code and getting that part to be more
effective and if that's not the biggest
problem your organization has at the
moment then hire someone who can fix
your biggest problem that might not be
me so I have some other just general
questions about someone coaching so like
is there an ideal team size does it work
better for smaller teams larger teams
when you're working in Ensemble you need
to have enough people in the room that
have all the skills you need to deliver
the the task you're working on and it's
usually around four to six people is a
good size for an
ensemble I've no reason to believe that
actually if you needed more people than
that because the the skills were lacking
in the room I think it could still be
effective with a lot more people than
that in The Ensemble but my experience
is mostly with teams of about four to
six people and that seems to me quite a
sweet spot for a team size for software
development
uh so that's what I would normally
recommend is there an upper bound that
you've seen like over a certain number
of people just gets too many voices it
depends on the facilitation and the
nature of the problem you're trying to
work on I found it more difficult and
stressful when you've got seven or eight
people and that's why I usually advise
let's let's take a smaller group at
least when we're still learning and this
is the first time we're doing Ensemble
it's probably better to have a smaller
group I wouldn't want to put a limit on
it
particularly with experienced teams with
hard problems yeah I imagine there's
some self-control of like not blurting
stuff out either if you're if you're in
the audience you if everybody's talking
at once that just gets to be too much so
like having that the discipline yeah
yeah so that's one of the skills of of
Ensemble is knowing what is my role at
the moment and how can I best contribute
and often that's not by speaking your
mind all the time it's by picking your
moment to speak so another question I
have is how often do teams typically do
coaching sessions and is there value in
having them spaced out so they have time
to practice between or you try to cram
them all together to learn as much as
possible in a short period of time or
I've done it a few different ways you
can schedule a block of two weeks with
coaching every day and then you know a
couple of months off and then another
two weeks coaching every day that's kind
of intense at The Other Extreme I've
done it one coaching session per week
for for like 10 weeks or or so and that
is much more relaxed and the team has
much more time between to practice what
they learned in the learning hour in the
last session but it takes ages to get
anything done and and you lose a little
bit of context I think between the
sessions and then another 10we block is
going to be like a year away uh so and
that's again I think it's a bit long so
at the moment I'm generally trying to
schedule 10 half days of of coaching in
a period of 3 to five weeks as a kind of
medium between those so can you talk
about like the biggest success story
that you've seen from common coaching do
you have a team where like they started
out one way and then after a bunch of
coaching they kind of transform the way
they work I think I already told you
that success story okay that was Lan's
team that I worked with yeah other
success
stories I worked with a team that was
full of quite relatively Junior
Developers
and there was just one person in the
team who was a bit more experienced but
still they were really struggling quite
a bit with the code that they were
working on the design wasn't very
optimal was a bit bit Legacy and they
they because they were also Junior they
they were really struggling to make
progress with it so through some
coaching sessions we learned some skills
around refactoring and in particular
extract method naming as a process
think just Cod smells and and names of
refactorings and at the end of a
coaching block the person with a bit
more experience was like well I feel so
much more confident now talk with the
rest of my team and explain to all these
Junior developers what it is that they
should be doing so he felt a lot more
confident and I could see that these
Junior developers they were just
starting to Blossom they were just
starting to get it and feel confident
enough to to make changes so I thought
that that was a a really good story of
of how coaching just helped that team to
go from barely managing what they were
being asked to do to actually being able
to collaborate and make progress yeah
that's good so can you talk a little bit
about the samon coaching society and
what its goals are and why you founded
it I've been doing this style of
coaching for a few years and and found
it to be really beneficial and I wanted
to share my methods with the world
because I think there's such a need out
there for technical coaching there are
so many teams struggling with code that
is difficult to to work with and to
maintain and they need to learn
refactoring skills they need to learn
test driven development and the
resources that are out there there are
you know there were code Carters and
coding dojos but I think technical
coaching is what I found to really work
and I wanted to spread this so I I wrote
the book explaining it as a start and in
association with that I registered the
website samon coaching. org and I
started to publish more materials and
and discover other people doing
technical coaching and some of the my
colleagues at the time were like well we
could set something up that would be
bigger than just us in this company so
we founded a not for-profit organization
and the reason it's not for-profit is so
that people from competitors basically
could join and we could share our
materials and we could help one another
and in a way that wouldn't be for profit
for any of those particular
organizations you're not helping your
competitor you're you're helping a
community the whole point of this
basically is to grow the market because
there's a huge need for it and we're
just trying to say well if we help one
another and do a better job and people
benefit from the coaching and tell their
friends then that's going to benefit
everybody so let's help one another and
share our materials so it's a a big
coaching kind of collective collabor of
type space well yeah in one sense that's
the mission of the not for-profit is to
support technical coaches everywhere
although I have put some limits on who
can actually become a member of the not
for-profit because I want it also to be
a way to develop samon coaching as a
method I mean what I wrote down in my
book was what I was doing at the time
and I'm totally prepared for that not to
be forever what samon coaching is I want
the method to develop and be improved
and others to contribute their wisdom
and knowledge about how the good best
ways are for for doing technical
coaching and I wanted there to be a
trusted group who were in control of the
future of samon coaching so the society
owns the brand and the website and we
have a board and we have you know
meetings and and procedures for how to
admit new members who we trust and uh
we're working on ways to communicate
updates to the samon coaching method so
that it can evolve and grow and change
and not always just be what I wrote in
my book a few years ago yeah I think
that's probably why is a lot of things
like test driven development and some of
those things like they mean a lot of
different things to different people so
having a group to kind of curate that
meaning I think is is useful so it
doesn't get too diffuse so you mentioned
something there just wrapping up you
mentioned that many teams struggle
dealing with existing code why do you
think that is it's about skill and
culture a lot of developers actually
didn't learn how to refactor at
University and they're not learning it
on the job there's not enough knowledge
transfer from more senior to more Junior
developers so a lot of developers don't
actually know how to improve design of
existing code or at least not how to do
it safely so that's one of the problems
that they don't know how to do it the
other problem is they don't given time
like they need to ask for permission to
improve the design of the code they're
working with and and that somehow the
managers should decide that I think
that's the wrong way to look at this
there needs to be a culture in the
development team of we improve the
design this is how we work we support
one another we expect that when a new
feature gets built a certain amount of
that time will be spent improving the
existing design to make it easier to add
that feature that we're not just going
to shoehorn it into the design we had
before and so I think this is why
organizations get into trouble because
they don't have the skill and they don't
have the culture and it's not enough
just to say okay developers right now
you've got a refactoring Sprint or a a
quality week where you can fix these
problems that's a kind of like a one
oneoff sheet that doesn't actually solve
the problem you need it to be a
continuing ongoing way of working and
with skill developers who know how to do
this so my last question that just kind
of popped into in my head was do you
think there's a role for katas in
education cuz I I feel like a lot of
computer science type education is
starting from a green field right here's
this problem go solve it and a lot of
what we do in industry in production is
you come in and there there's already
this code base and it's like hey add
this feature but the code base doesn't
really lend itself to adding that new
feature yet yeah I think there's a lot
that could be improved about educating
new developers it's not really my area
though honestly I've always work with
people who are already professional
developers and that's where I've applied
all these techniques so I think if I'm
going to talk about Computer Science
Education and so on I'm just speculating
but if there are Educators who are
interested and want to to use my code
Carters I would absolutely support them
I know my code Carters are being used a
lot for for job interviews so students
already pract practice on them to
prepare for job interviews so there's
already knowledge about them in that
Community but but yeah probably there
could be more okay great thanks for
coming and sitting down talking to me
for SC radio this is Sam tager thank you
for joining us thank you for having
me thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by it
e software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licens under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for listening